[Music]
there's an extensive scientific
literature describing the positive
impact of dietary plant compounds on
overall health and longevity however
it's only now becoming clear that the
consumption of diets rich in plant foods
can influence neuro inflammation brain
inflammation leading to the expression
of cytoprotective cell protective and
restorative proteins just over the last
decade remarkable progress has been made
to realize that oxidative stress and
chronic low-grade inflammation are major
risk factors underlying brain aging so
no wonder antioxidant in
anti-inflammatory foods may help
the brain is especially vulnerable to
free radical attack oxidative stress due
to its high fat content and its cauldron
of high metabolic activity
you don't want your brains to go rancid
so you'd think one of the major fat
soluble dietary antioxidants like beta
carotene would step in
but the major carotenoid concentrated in
the brain is actually lutein
the brain just preferentially sucks it
up for example if you look at the oldest
old like in the georgia centenarian
study
recognizing that oxidation is involved
in age-related cognitive decline they
figured dietary antioxidants may play a
role in its prevention or delay so it
looked at eight different ones vitamin a
vitamin e on down the list and only
lutein was significantly related to
better cognition
now in this study they looked at brain
tissue on autopsy by then it's a little
too late so how could you study the
effects of diet on the brain while
you're still alive i mean if only there
was a way we could physically look into
the living brain
with our own two eyes
there is
the retina the back of our eyeball is
actually an extension of our central
nervous system and out pouching of the
brain during development
and right in the middle there's a spot
this is what the doctor sees when they
look into your eye with that bright
light that spot
called the macula is our hd camera where
you get the highest resolution vision
and it's packed with lutein and indeed
levels in the retina correspond to
levels in the rest of your brain
so your eyes can be a window into your
brain
so now we can finally do studies on live
people to see if diet can affect lutein
levels in the eyes which reflects lutein
levels in the brain and see if that
correlates with improvements in
cognitive function and indeed
significant correlations exist between
the amount of macular pigment these
plant pigments like lutein in your eye
and cognitive test scores
you can demonstrate this on functional
mri scans suggesting lutein and a
related plant pigment called zeaxanthin
promote cognitive functioning in old age
by enhancing neural efficiency the
efficiency by which our nerves
communicate
like check out this cool study on white
matter integrity using something called
the diffusion tensor imaging which
provides unique insights into brain
network connectivity allowing you to
follow the nerve tracks throughout the
brain and researchers were able to show
enhanced circuit integrity based on how
much lutein and zeaxanthin they could
see in people's eyes further evidence of
a meaningful relationship between diet
and integrity of our brains particularly
in regions vulnerable to age-related
decline
so so do do alzheimer's patients have
less of this macular pigment
significantly less lutein in their eyes
significantly less lutein in their blood
and a higher occurrence of macular
degeneration where this pigment layer
gets destroyed
the thickness of this plant pigment
layer in your eyes can be measured and
may be a potential marker for the
beginnings of alzheimer's
let's not wait that long though we know
macular pigment densities related to
cognitive function in older people what
about during middle age
one apparent consequence of aging
appears to be loss of some aspects of
cognitive control which starts out early
in mid-adulthood
but not in everybody suggesting maybe
something like diet could be driving
some of the differences here's a measure
of cognitive control showing younger on
average do better than older adults
but older adults who have high macular
pigment lots of lutein in the back of
their eyes do significantly better these
results suggest that the protective role
of carotenoids like lutein within the
brain may be evident during early and
middle adulthood decades prior to the
onset of more apparent cognitive decline
later in life
you can take 20 year olds and show
superior auditory function in those with
more macular pigment in their eyes
look the auditory system our hearing
like the rest of our central nervous
system is ultimately constructed and
maintained by diet and is therefore not
surprisingly sensitive to dietary intake
throughout life all the way back
to childhood
higher macular pigment is associated
with higher academic achievement among
school children you can look into a
kid's eyes and get some sense of how
well they may do in subjects like math
and writing
this is finding is important because
macular lutein is modifiable and can be
manipulated by dietary intake
okay okay so where is lutein found
the avocado and egg industries like to
boast about how much of these macular
pigments they have in their products but
the real superstars are dark green leafy
vegetables a half a cup of kale has 50
times more than an egg
a spinach salad or a 50 egg omelet
and the earlier the better pregnant and
breastfeeding women should definitely be
checking off my daily dozen green
servings
but it's also apparently never too late
while some age-related cognitive decline
is to be expected these effects may be
less pronounced among those eating more
green and leafy
but you don't know for sure
until you put it to the test which we'll
explore
next
[Music]